{
  "reference_number": "12268",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Stopping all new coal mines, particularly on our public conservation lands and in Water Conservation Reserves"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1. Climate change is one of the biggest challenges facing people in poverty in New Zealand and in developing countries. It would be\n\nunethical for NZ to ignore the impact climate change is having on our neighbours in the Pacific and across the developing world. 2.\nClimate Change is a global problem – it cannot be tackled by countries in isolation. In our farming families view, New Zealand must\n\ndemonstrate global leadership and match its bold domestic emissions reduction agenda: by having an equally ambitious climate\nchange strategy abroad. 3. Access to climate finance is a matter of climate justice – those who have contributed least to the causes\nof climate change are typically the most vulnerable to its impacts and have the least resources to respond. This is unacceptable and\n\nmust be remedied. 4. We must take responsibility for our global emissions and the climate impacts that we have contributed to. It’s\nvery important that all New Zealanders have their say on how we make the shift to a zero carbon future here in New Zealand but in\n\nour view we must also help the world’s most vulnerable communities across the Pacific adjust to the impacts on climate change. 5.\nWe must ensure that the Zero Carbon Bill is transparent. This means the bill must include a requirement to produce annual reports\n\nabout New Zealand’s international climate change contributions in order to ensure that the Pacific countries get the support they\nneed and can plan to adapt to their changing environment. 6.Transparency in the Bill will promote public engagement and political\naccountability. Kiwis will then be able to understand the international contributions we are making and as a nation, we will be able to\n\nstand tall that we are supporting our Pacific neighbours adapt to their climate change reality. 7. It is time for New Zealand to lead\nagain. We have a history of global leadership: we were the first country to give women the vote, the first to become nuclear free and\n\nwe have no commercial GE food crops or animals, no cloning of animals. We have a valuable ZERO TOLERANCE Policy for any GE\ncontent in imported seeds, including adventitious presence.. It is time to take another giant step towards climate justice globally. 8.\n\nNew Zealand has demonstrated global leadership with our commitment to stopping oil and gas exploration – now let us continue that\nmoral leadership and include transparency in what and how we support climate change efforts abroad. 9. We ask that the Zero\nCarbon Bill prioritizes supporting the most vulnerable people in the Pacific. 10. NO new coal mines in the North Island or South Island.\n\nWe support the Minister of Conservation Hon Eugenie Sage's recent excellent decision, DECLINING the application by Stevenson\nMining Ltd/ RAngitira Developments Ltd for a new open cast coal mine on public conservation lands (in an Outstanding Landscape,\n\nabove Westport). The Stevenson Mining LTD/ Rangitira Developments proposal for a new open cast coal mine in the Buller District\nCouncil \"Water Conservation Reserve\" (approximately 100 hectares) and on our public conservation lands (12 hectares) must be\n\nstopped in its entirety. It would increase the Bullers negative contribute to climate change, put the town of Westport and the Buller /\nWest Coast in general- particularly but not limited to coastal communities already experiencing severe erosion- further at risk from\n\nviolent storms. We support the new government putting a ban on all new coal mines. In our view, ensuring that existing mines are\noperated to best practice standards, and that full robust remediation is done to best environmental standards, will retain and create\nethical jobs (during the period during which we transition to safe and clean, renewable energy). Thank you for the opportunity to\n\nmake a submission, I wish to be heard at any hearing that may occur. Thank you!"
    }
  ]
}
